Florence Levin Lockshin Papers, 1924-1995
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Florence Levin Lockshin papers
1924-1995
Lockshin, Florence Levin, 1910-1997
MS 405
14 boxes (6.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Composer and pianist. The papers focus mainly on Lockshin's musical compositions and include scores; recordings of performances; plus files of correspondence, publicity and memorabilia related to performances of her work. There are also a series of unpublished poems written by Lockshin in her later life. Materials include writings, speech notes, correspondence, musical scores, and audio recordings.
Florence Helen Levin was born March 24, 1910 in Columbus, Ohio, the daughter of Samuel M. and Jennie (Klein) Levin. Levin had an early interest in music, winning competitions in concert piano in her teen-age years. She majored in music at Ohio State University, where she met, and in 1933 married, Samuel D. Lockshin. The couple had twin sons, Richard and Michael. After earning a B.S. in music in 1931, she continued to perform and was a founder of the Four Piano Quartet in Mansfield, Ohio. Most of Lockshin's early compositions were for the piano. She wrote and often arranged works to be played by the Quartet. In 1951, the Four Piano Quartet represented Ohio at the 26th Biennial Convention of the National Federation of Music Clubs.
In 1952, Lockshin moved to Northampton, Massachusetts, where she studied composition at Smith College (1952-55) under the tutelage of composer Alvin Etler. From this point, Lockshin turned her attention to larger ensembles, composing primarily for orchestra or chorus and orchestra. Her first such work was The Cycle (1956-57), a ballet commissioned by the Smith College Dance Department.
In 1959, Lockshin began to incorporate folk themes into her work in Annie Bradley's Tune, a piece based on a short melody sung to Lockshin's twin sons by their African-American nurse. Paean Santa Maria de Guadalupe (1962) is based on a hymn Lockshin heard penitents sing as they approached the basilica in Mexico City. When her husband's work as a management consultant took them to Arizona in the late 1960s, Lockshin's response to the music she heard there was the orchestral suite Scavarr (1969), based on Yuma and Mojave themes. After retirement, Samuel Lockshin worked for the International Executive Service Corps as a volunteer business consultant in Columbia, Venezuela, and Panama. ¡Cumbia! Fantasy on a Columbian Folk Dance (1977) was inspired by music heard during the Lockshins' many trips to various countries in Central and South America.
Interest in women composers spurred by the women's movement, plus interest in all things American connected with the country's bicentennial in 1976, led to a series of performances of Lockshin's work during the 1960s and 70s. Annie Bradley's Tune was the most-performed, both in the U.S. and in concerts of American music in Venezuela and Panama.
Florence Levin Lockshin died in Naples, Florida, on September 26, 1997.
The Florence Levin Lockshin Papers consist of 6.25 linear feet of biographical material, subject files, photographs, student notes, speeches, writings, publicity, memorabilia, musical scores, and recordings.
The papers contain limited biographical and personal information, focusing primarily on Lockshin's musical compositions. The bulk of the papers consists of scores, dating from 1959 to 1982. In addition there are recordings of several of her works and files of correspondence, publicity, and memorabilia related to performances of the works. There is also a file which demonstrates Lockshin's tireless efforts to interest various musicians in performing her pieces. Subject files on music attest to the sudden interest in women composers fired by the women's movement.
Later in life, Lockshin turned to the written word, producing a series of poems. In addition to manuscript and typescript versions of the poems there is material related to Lockshin's efforts to find publishers for these works.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Biographical and Miscellaneous Materials
II. Speeches and Writings
III. Muscial Compositions
Florence Levin Lockshin Musical Compositions
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.
History of the Collection
The Florence Levin Lockshin Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Richard and Zahra Zakeri Lockshin and Michael and Jane Roberts Lockshin in 2000.
Search Terms
Lockshin, Florence Levin, 1910-1997; Composition (Music)--History--20th century--Sources; Music--Manuscripts--United States; Pianists--United States--Sources; Women musicians--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women composers--United States--History--20th century--Sources
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL AND MISCELLANEOUS MATERIALS 1930-90, undated, .25 linear ft.
  This series consists of general biographical material, subject files on a variety of musical topics, photographs, and student notes.
- SERIES II. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS 1961-91, undated, .25 linear ft.
  The speeches portion of this series contains a typescript and manuscript for undated talks to unidentified groups. The writings portion consists mainly of manuscript and typescript versions of poems by Florence Lockshin. In addition there are a few files of material related to Lockshin's attempts to find publishers for her poetry.
- SERIES III. MUSICAL COMPOSITIONS 1924-95, undated, 5.75 linear ft.
  This series is organized into four subseries: General, Performances, Scores, and Recordings.
  General contains Lockshin's descriptions of her musical compositions, research materials, and miscellaneous correspondence related to some of the compositions.
  Performances consists primarily of correspondence, news clippings, memorabilia, programs, and publicity related to specific performances of her works. These are arranged alphabetically by title of work and then chronologically by performance date. There is also one folder of material related to Lockshin's efforts to interest other musicians in performing her music.
  Scores consists of various versions of Lockshin's compositions from manuscript fragments to master sheets to full scores with performance and revision notes. They are arranged alphabetically by title of the work. Scores of student work and unidentified fragments are filed at the end of the scores. There is also one box of duplicate scores available for loan.
  Recordings consists of phonograph records, and cassette and reel-to-reel audiotapes of various performances of Lockshin's pieces. They are arranged by format and then alphabetically by title of the work. There are also a few cassettes of Cumbia music used as research for her work by that name.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL AND MISCELLANEOUS MATERIALS 1930-90, undated
  - Biographical articles, 1970-90, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960-87, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum vitae, circa 1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memorabilia, 1930-58, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Music subject files
    - General, 1982-88, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - American Composers Alliance, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Music Center, 1963-82 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Women composers, 1975-85, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - WYNC radio show "Overture to Women," 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Smith College, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Student notes (probably Ohio State University)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Music 603, "Music in France," undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- SERIES II. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS 1961-91, undated
  - Speeches
    - "The Jew in the Field of Art," undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Modern Music and Musicians, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Writing
    - General, 1961-85, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Publication contacts, ideas, and leads, 1980-87, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Aye Cumbia," undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Muriel," undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Shrewsbury Shottische," 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Small Vehicle," 1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Poetry
      - Correspondence re: publication, 1984-91, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Manuscripts, 1956-89, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Manuscript notebooks, 1983-85 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
      - Typescripts, 1983-85, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- SERIES III. MUSICAL COMPOSITIONS 1924-95, undated
  - General
    - Descriptions of compositions, 1957-77, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Do Not Go Gentle Into That Good Night text copyright: correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Independent Music Publishers, Inc., 1947-81, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Indian project, 1969-72, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Notes and fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Paean Santa Maria de Guadalupe: notes and research, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Scavarr: research, 1932, 1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Performances
    - Contacts, ideas, and leads, 1953-95, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, clippings, programs, memorabilia, and publicity
      - Annie Bradley's Tune
        - Columbus Symphony Orchestra (1960), 1957-60, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
        - Indianapolis Symphony Orchestra (1961), 1958-61, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
        - Brooklyn Philharmonia (1967), 1966-67, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
        - Westchester Symphony Orchestra (1967), 1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
        - Orquesta Sinfonica de Panama (1975), 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
        - Orquesta Sinfonica Venezuela (1976), 1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - The Cycle, Smith College (1957), 1956-57, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Paean, Stockton Symphony (1976), 1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Scores
    - Annie Bradley's Tune: Fantasy on a Negro Folk Song for orchestra, 1959
      - Full score
        - Manuscript (Box 4, Folder 1)
        - Original version (Box 4, Folder 2)
        - With performance notes and revisions (Box 4, Folder 3)
        - Revised (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Anniversary (Yahrzeit) song, 1949: manuscript scores (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Aural: Verse for Orchestra (original title Rallentando), 1962-63
      - Piano score (manuscript) (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Full score
        - Original version (Box 4, Folder 7)
        - Revised (Box 4, Folder 8)
        - Master sheets (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Instrumental parts
        - Manuscript (Box 4, Folder 10)
        - Master sheets (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Based on Blues for Mixed Quintet (clarinet, horn, trumpet, trombone, and piano), 1978
      - Full score
        - Manuscript (Box 5, Folder 1)
        - Master sheets (Box 5, Folder 2)
        - With handwritten revisions (Box 5, Folder 3)
        - Revised (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Cowboy Waltz (song), undated: manuscript scores (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - ¡Cumbia! Fantasy on a Columbian Folk-Dance (based on two themes by Efrain Mejia) for Orchestra, 1977
      - Full score
        - Manuscript (Box 5, Folder 6)
        - Original version (Box 5, Folder 7)
        - "Final Simple Version" (Box 5, Folder 8)
        - Master sheets (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Instrumental parts: master sheets (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - The Cycle: Ballet for Orchestra, 1956-57
      - Full score
        - Manuscript (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - With notes for revision (Box 6, Folder 2)
        - Revised (Box 6, Folder 3)
        - Master sheets (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Instrumental parts
        - Manuscript (Box 6, Folder 5)
        - Master sheets (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
      - "Changes in Orch" with performance notes (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Do Not Go Gentle Into That Good Night for Men's Chorus with Instrumental Accompaniment (Dylan Thomas), 1959
      - Full score
        - Manuscript (Box 7, Folder 1)
        - Original version (Box 7, Folder 2)
        - Master sheets (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Instrumental Parts: master sheets (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Do Not Go Gentle Into That Good Night for Men's Chorus with Instrumental Accompaniment (Dylan Thomas), revised version (lower), 1978: manuscript, full score, and vocal score (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Dusty Baby (song, music and lyrics by FLL), circa 1982: manuscript scores (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Introduction, Lament and Protest (Memorial to Fay August Bender) for Orchestra, 1964-67
      - Manuscript drafts (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Full score
        - Manuscript (Box 8, Folder 2)
        - Original version (Box 8, Folder 3)
        - With handwritten corrections (Box 8, Folder 4)
        - Master sheets (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Instrumental parts: master sheets (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Lament (from Introduction, Lament and Protest): corrected score (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Paean Santa Maria de Guadalupe for Orchestra, 1962
      - Manuscript drafts (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Full score
        - Manuscript (Box 9, Folder 2)
        - Original version (Box 9, Folder 3)
        - With handwritten corrections and performance notes (Box 9, Folder 4)
        - Master sheets (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Instrumental parts: master sheets (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Prospice for Mixed Chorus and Orchestra (text Robert Browning), 1980 (to Gonzalo Castellanos Y.)
      - Manuscript and drafts (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Score (master sheet transfer) (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Scavarr (Songs of the Yuma and Mojave Indians) Suite for Orchestra, 1969 (Earlier name: Yuma County Impressions)
      - Manuscript drafts (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Full score
        - Manuscript (Box 10, Folder 2)
        - Original (master sheet transfer) (Box 10, Folder 3)
        - With handwritten corrections (Box 10, Folder 4)
        - Master sheets (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Instrumental parts: master sheets (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Sonata for Four Pianos, undated: manuscript score (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Sonata for Two Pianos, undated: manuscript score (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Song for Women's Chorus with Instrumental Accompaniment (text Christina Rosetti), 1980
      - Manuscript and drafts (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Master sheet transfer (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Song Form for Orchestra, 1961 (former name: Song and Blues)
      - Manuscript and drafts (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Full score
        - Manuscript (Box 11, Folder 2)
        - Master sheet transfer (Box 11, Folder 3)
        - Master sheets (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Instrumental parts: master sheets (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Trilogy: Poems of Prospice (consists of Do Not Go Gentle Into That Good Night, Song, and Prospice): score, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Variations on Five Notes for Four Pianos, 1951-53: manuscript score and drafts (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Waltz for Four Pianos, 1953: manuscript score and drafts (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Student pieces, 1924, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Student pieces, Smith College (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Fragments and miscellaneous manuscripts, undated (Box 11, Folder 11-12)
  - Scores-Loan Copies
    - Annie Bradley's Tune (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Aural (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Based on Blues (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - ¡Cumbia! (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - The Cycle (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Do Not Go Gentle Into That Good Night (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Introduction, Lament and Protest (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Propice (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Song (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Trilogy (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Recordings
    - Phonograph records
      - Annie Bradley's Tune
        - Columbus, 1960 (Box 13)
        - Indianapolis, 1961 (Box 13)
      - The Cycle (?) (Box 13)
      - Variations on Five Notes for Four Pianos, rehearsal, Mansfield, OH, undated (Box 13)
      - Waltz for Four Pianos, 24 Apr 1951 (Box 13)
    - Audiotapes: cassette
      - Annie Bradley's Tune
        - Columbus Symphony rehearsal tape, 1960 (Box 13)
        - Orquesta Sinfonica Venezuela, 11 Jul 1976 "taken at concert by Sam"
          - Complete concert (Box 13)
          - Annie Bradley's Tune only (Box 13)
        - Panama City, 1975 (Box 13)
        - WNYC, 2 Jul 1978 (Box 13)
        - "not clear" (Box 13)
      - Once de Novembre Cumbia (Efrain Mejia) by Siglo XX, Hotel el Prado, 1972 (Box 13)
      - Cumbia Columbiana, 11 Nov, "native group" (Box 13)
      - Cumbia groups, 1972 (Box 13)
    - Audiotapes: reel-to-reel
      - Annie Bradley's Tune
        - Columbus Symphony Orchestra, 1960
          - Monophonic 1960 (Box 13)
          - Stereophonic (Box 13)
          - Monaural, edited version (Box 13)
        - Indianapolis Symphony Orchestra, 5 Nov 1961 1960 (Box 14)
        - Panama City, 1975 (Box 14)
        - Orquesta Sinfonica Venezuela, 11 Jul 1976 (Box 14)
        - Unknown performers (Box 14)
      - The Cycle, undated (Box 14)
- Florence Levin Lockshin Musical Compositions
  - Annie Bradley's Tune: Fantasy on a Negro Folk Tune for Orchestra 1959
  - Anniversary (Yahrzeit) (song, 1949)
  - Aural: Verse for Orchestra 1962-63
  - Based on Blues for Mixed Quintet 1978
  - Cowboy Waltz (song, undated)
  - ¡Cumbia! Fantasy on a Columbian Folk Dance for Orchestra 1977
  - The Cycle: Ballet for Orchestra 1956-57
  - Do Not Go Gentle Into That Good Night for Men's Chorus with Instrumental Accompaniment (1959, text: Dylan Thomas)
  - Dusty Baby (song, 1982)
  - Introduction, Lament, and Protest for Orchestra 1964-67
  - Paean Santa Maria de Guadalupe for Orchestra 1962
  - Prospice for Mixed Chorus and Orchestra (1980, text: Robert Browning)
  - Scavarr (Songs of the Yuma and Mohave Indians) Suite for Orchestra 1969
  - Sonata for Four Pianos undated
  - Sonata for Two Pianos undated
  - Song for Women's Chorus with Instrumental Accompaniment (1980, text: Christina Rossetti)
  - Song Form for Orchestra 1961
  - Trilogy: Poems of Prospice (consists of Do Not Go Gentle Into That Good Night, Song, and Prospice)
  - Variations on Five Notes for Four Pianos 1951-53
  - Waltz for Four Pianos 1953